all right
welcome to parallax lectures i'm your
host
thoma mark this is the i think
sixth episode of uh this fairly new
format
um our guest speaker
our guest lecturer today is professor
raul eschermann he's a slavicist and he
teaches
i hope that i get that right
at the university in munich
and he's the author author of several
books on
performatism a topic which is about to
speak
um today so i welcome um
raul eshelman would you please join in
welcome can you can you
um click on the microphone button so we
can hear you
um i'm not hearing you
okay yeah no we no we've got it now
we've got it
okay so how are you doing i'm doing fine
i'm
obviously in a virtual room these are
the virtual halls of the ludwig
maximilian's universitate in munich
right i'm of course actually at home
right in the time of uh kovid and i'm
very happy to be
to be here in the south of germany
you're coming from the south of germany
but you're not actually a german right
you're coming from the united states or
it's a very long story but to make the
story short i would say that i was
raised in america but that i am
what is called a um a an in
in lance i'm an inlender
in terms of education i've studied
i studied did my m.a ph.d and
habilitation in germany and i've lived
in germany for over 40 years right
right and you you um you are you're a
slavicist
so how how does that relate to to
performatism is there a connection there
or is that
a separate separate uh
field of study um it uh it it overlaps i
it started out with
uh i started out studying a
uh russian viktor pierle who was a kind
of a buddhist a kind of a crazy buddhist
and that led me to the idea that what he
was doing was something that was
was more universal that was something
that wasn't just confined
to to russian literature or to him and
that led me on to
basically to to the whole notion of of
performatism
right so you uh will give a lecture
today what is it about
uh it's about performance in other words
it's an attempt just to
to give an overview of uh of the theory
itself
what it is what it is not this is also
important and also
to eventually to tie it in a little bit
with
what the social issues with uh with the
problems of globalization right okay
perfect
so how that will work i will make you
now the host you will have your lecture
and
after that we can have like uh like a
discussion or q a
or like an we can just be open about
what will happen and see
how that all goes would that be okay for
you that's okay for me i assume i'll
disappear from the screen and that what
you will now
no i disappear from the screen i make
you know
uh make you know the host okay uh
and now you have the floor okay thank
you very much so
i'll start my powerpoint presentation i
think which uh
you can hopefully see and which also
hopefully will
function this is okay so
uh here we are the uh the the the title
of this
introduction is the performatism is
transcendence
and belief after post-modernism and
one of my basic ideas is that
in this new cultural development we are
able to
experience or apprehend transcendence
and
and and and belief in in the form of art
in the form of literature
uh in in all sorts of different media
and
the some of the titles you see here or
some of the
works you see here are indicative of
that or
and i'll go into some of them in the
course of the lecture of course i can't
do everything here what i'd like to
start out is
of course is what is performatism that's
the easiest
um easiest or the most obvious
question and uh performatism as i
define it is an across-the-board
cultural reaction to post-modernism that
began sometime
in the mid-1990s it may best be
described
as an epical development that replaces
postmodern irony and skepticism
with artistically mediated belief and
the experience of transcendence and
this
this is a lot more complicated than uh
obviously than it
first sounds this is not a religious
revival but it is it tries to describe
the way
that art literature film
all even architecture forces us into
positions where we
believe certain things what i would like
to start off with is
what performatism is not because when i
give these lectures i'm very often
told and not informed that
it's a simply a repetition of modernism
and that it is or that is simply
continuing something that
post-modernism already did so
post-modern uh
performance is not a return to modernism
and proformatism is not
a continuation of post-modernism
and to explain why that's the case
i'll do a very very quick and very
superficial run-through
of of modernism and and modernism
high modernism 1910s and 20s
is devoted to radical innovation to
destroying convention
the search for authenticity the search
for the essence of things
uh the radical fracturing and reshaping
of the human subject
and is also very closely involved with
utopianism with
revolution in in many cases and here
uh obviously you could name dozens and
dozens of people hemingway bresch
takafka
myakovsky they're these are all
in a certain sense typical of this sort
of
of attitude of cultural a cultural
strategy um to give a
also a visual example of how this works
uh modernism seeks to shock it seems to
uh it seems to sh it tries to shatter
convention
as this urinal that uh marcel duchamp
the famous urinal that he
placed in a museum uh but
typical in another respect is the the
fact that uh
that the human subject it's him him or
herself is shattered
by the artist here by casimir malievich
in his
picture of a knife grinder who is
completely dissolved
fragmented fractured and
enters into the work that the dynamics
of the work that he's doing
and finally perhaps the most extreme
expression of this the black square of
uh casimir malievic which opens up a
kind of utopian
potential beyond the the work itself
now in architecture once more very very
briefly and superficially you have a
kind of
the a a three-dimensional equivalent of
the
uh black square in the seagram building
from
niss van der rohe and this sort of
building
is meant to put to an end all questions
of style
uh forever because function it it
it then embodies pure or is supposed to
embody pure
functionality so now what happens with
modernism it continues to develop in
into what we what is sometimes called
late modernism
here we find in very often the opposite
of what we saw before a return
to stylized representations of reality
we find hierarchy structure and order
again in in
in art and literature and also the human
subject is now has been reconstructed
and is
subjected or subordinated to these this
higher order or
hierarchy and uh here utopian ideals are
realized very often in totalitarian
systems of
political order so uh what happens next
is that
we have once more to give visual
examples here
a very famous painting by otto thistle
showing a
german farmer's family the
figures realistically stylized idealized
and also atomized they're not looking at
one another
yeah they're part of a higher a higher
order
here the next example
from socialist from socialist realism
where you see happy happy peasant
women working in a collective part of
stalin's own dream own utopian dream
that he tried to impose
on the soviet union and finally
we have salvador dali in
in the west who is obviously not uh
political in the direct sense of the
word but who
imposes a paranoid order on on
on the viewer as you see here uh so
these are all things that are typical of
of
high modernism late modernism and
they uh come together in in and and form
a catastrophe
basically that we have the gulag
in russia we have auschwitz in in
germany and we have uh
hiroshima and nagasaki in the west that
these are
that is that the the the modernist is
striving for
order uh for destroying the individual
for also technological innovation leads
to these
massive catastrophes these disasters
and the the question is how do artists
how to
how do writers how do people involved in
culture deal with this
and the answer is basically
what we call what we today call
post-modernism
and the post-modernisms the
post-modernists
main goal is our main question main
problem
how do we avoid the disastrous mistakes
of modernism and uh
this is basically the the answers to
this question
are negative that there's no more
radical innovation there is no more
striving for a new
utopian order there is no search for an
authentic sense of being or an essence
as in modernism there is no radical
reshaping of human beings
and the main goal of art becomes
disillusionment
that the the idea that we should not
follow
our illusions that we can make the world
better that we can
improve man that any of these things
all these things are now subjected to
very stringent
critiques and the way that
post-modernism goes about it
is to proclaim the end of history
that is that everything new there's
nothing more new because
innovation has led to disaster uh
everything new is merely
an ironic repositioning of what is old
and known the human being the human
subject is thought of
in a defensive way as a fleeting
disentered victim and this
subject has has certain strategies that
it can use to
to resist to avoid oppression
it can appropriate other other people's
positions
in an ironic way to make it less
subject to persecution uh the subject
can also
avoid oppression by dissolving into the
context in which it happens to find
itself
and it can also play with ironically
with
false signs uh as as a kind of a
positive
option it can simulate so these are all
things that
the the postmodern subject post-modern
heroes
post-modern heroines that do in in film
and works of literature in plays etc
um here as we are
well know that virtual reality becomes
much more
important than the direct authentic
experience of reality which is now seen
as some sort of
self deception as a modernist illusion
and simply to give a few examples uh to
make the point
clear here you have andy warhol's famous
uh
campbell soup cans uh they here
art is ironically shown to be equivalent
to
advertising and advertising to art uh
art has to sell
on the one hand and advertising has to
make an aesthetic impression
also in order to to also to sell so that
and warhol of course was both he was
both an advertising man and an artist
and was involved with both
um another simply examples which
show uh how postmodernism ironizes
the the modernist tradition here you
have duchamp's
urinal once more but it is now
gold-plated
signifying that it is it has become an
object a commodity in the art world
and here you see on the right hand side
you see a
also a urinal which is now adorned with
uh magnesium's red red square he also
did a red square
signifying also his collusion with uh
with with the communist uh government so
these uh sort of ironic plays with uh
with the tradition
are uh are repositioning of traditional
objects re-context
contextualizing of of
of already known cultural objects is
very typical of post-modernism
and here finally a an artistic
excuse me a an architectonic example
by philip johnson very famous building
in
new york where you have three styles
that are
competing you have the modernist style
you have a kind of an art naval style
and you have what looks like an 18th
century chippendale
dresser uh on the top so that uh
this this kind of building what this
kind of building says is essentially
that uh
uh that that style trying to find a
dominant style is about trying to find
assert power
and here on this this building in a
certain sense
unmasks unmasks
that that search as a as a
search for power and dominance as none
of these
styles really these styles canceled
one another out so to speak so this is
modernism postmodernism wrapped up in a
very quick way
and is uh as i will try to show that uh
performatism
which follows these two uh these two
epochs or these two developments
is is is quite different in the way it
goes about doing things
um so we now come to the counter logic
of
performatism which started roughly
speaking in the mid
1990s and has continued on up until
today and how does this this work now in
a positive way the first question that
uh or the main question that we have to
ask or that i think that
uh that writers uh that creative people
ask themselves
implicitly i don't think they actually
posed this question
explicitly but the problem was how to
stop
post-modern irony without returning to
modernist
utopianism or essentialism because if
you
go back to modernism if you start
repeating modernism you simply are going
to make the same
mistakes as the modernists and on top of
that you're going to simply be in the
ironic position of
simply repeating something old you're
not going to really be doing anything
new so
question is how do you go about doing
anything new
under these circumstances and
the way you do so at least the way that
i
have found to be
consistently present in in works of
literature art architecture
film etc is that performance works
construct
a formal closed-off inner space
an inner frame which i call an inner
frame
this is the first step you can think of
it there it is it's a it's a frame of
some kind
and within this frame we are now able to
experience
things like transcendence beauty truth
belief godliness love
that we previously were not able to
experience certainly not
in certainly not in post-modernism which
tried to try to which
tried to expose all these things as
illusions
and certainly not in the way that
modernism did it in the sense that we
now have an
artificial frame that is
that that imposes itself on us and makes
us feel
that what we're doing is in a certain
sense artificial i'll
return to that a little later um
what is important here is that this is
only possible
under particular formal conditions
supplied by the given work of art
and that these conditions are
constructed
and singular rather than authentic and
universal in other words a modernist
would claim that
uh whatever they were doing is something
that is uh
is is is is is exposing the essence of
something
uh or is is attuned to the essence of
and that this essential kind of
experience is
has a universal validity this is
something that
is not the case in performance and
these um these uh
these frames have a
performative character
derived from the word perform meaning
in la to go through form and what is
very very important here
is that the is the last point is that
these formal conditions are imposed on
us
and as are and are not on problem
unproblematic but in other words we're
experiencing
transcendence beauty love whatever
but at the same time the particular work
of art
of literature whatever is imposing
itself
formally upon us so that we have very
often have very little
choice about how we experience that work
and this interplay between
some positive experience of of of
bettering ourselves of transcending
ourselves
of experiencing beauty whatever
this is accompanied by force of some
kind so that there's always a kind of a
tension within
uh within the performance works between
these
usually very positive things and the use
of formal
force to uh to to to to to essentially
to force us to experience them
um i'm going to start out with a
uh whoop excuse me and i'm going to
start out with a
painting by the german painter of the
leipzig school
tim idol called reflections
and this painting is first of all
reminiscent if you're interested in art
is reminiscent of
german romantic painting it's in
particular of
the paintings of kaspar david friedrich
the german
romantic painter who here shows a
wanderer above a sea of mist
looking at sublime mountains
mountains that are in a certain sense an
expression of
godliness and when we go back to
uh when we go back to tim idle we see
something
rather different we see the same posture
but we don't really
see anything we of course don't see
anything
sublime directly in in front of us
now when we analyze this picture first
of all we can start out by saying that
the picture itself is is within a frame
the the outer frame you would say
which simply defines the painting this
simply a a given
of any painting uh this definition
allows us to make the connection to uh
to kaspar david friedesh or perhaps
other paintings that have a
a similar a similar theme and
we then can focus our attention on
the picture itself which presents us
with a kind of a unity with a kind of a
symmetry and an ambivalent symmetry
within the painting we have a reflection
and we have we call an original uh
figure
in the in the yellow in the yellow oil
skin
and this figure is analogous to the fig
to caspar david three there's a figure
he is opaque because we don't see him we
don't see his face
he's uh he or she is i suppose it's a
child
is tantalizing um and
uh this figure is not interested in
us he's not interested in in him or
herself
uh the figure is interested in what is
out there what is in a certain sense
uh potentially uh transcendent it
what else do we have in the picture we
have three dimensionality we have
realism at first it's a little bit
confusing when you look at the picture
but it's not too difficult to tell that
this is really a
three-dimensional this is a realistic
picture in a certain sense but what we
also have though is abstraction
in in the in particular here
in the the the background that the the
figure is looking into
so we have something comparable to the
friday
picture the possibility of transcendence
is suggested but remains ambivalent it's
not
clear if this is a wall or if this is
simply fog
uh we don't uh we we don't know
so if we summarize this we could say
that
we have a double frame that the work as
a whole confirms the symmetry
of the inner scene while
perhaps showing a way out in other words
we we
we don't uh we're not 100 sure that
there's a way out
but once more this is a figure that
gives us an apprehension of the
possibility of transcendence
without really realizing it in the same
explicit way that
that that regis does and the big
question is
as as with within all analyses of these
kind of works
be it paintings uh the paintings uh
films dramas whatever is this ironic
is this meant ironically and this is
something that each person
in a certain sense each viewer has to
answer
for his or herself um i do not find this
painting ironic in other words it's not
making
fun of of us and it's not making uh fun
of
the figure it's it's in a certain sense
uh perfectly
balanced uh between the uh
the these two postures um and
as i said here is a you're not
completely forced to uh to to accept
the the possibility of transcendence in
this picture uh
but it's it's it's difficult to avoid it
given
given the givens of the picture now
uh another example that is perhaps
that is from architecture and that is
perhaps a little bit
more obvious is the philharmonic hall in
hamburg
the albert philharmonic hall which
uh looks like an enormous
architect god has cut it out
cut out a chunk of the sea and here you
have the
the sea bottom the sea floor
this is this brown part and the this the
waves
have turned into a kind of a jelly and
are now
uh placed upon uh are now perched upon
the sea floor so um this is
i think an obvious act of an architect
um demonstrating transcendence
that it's it's an impossible act that
the architect
is now is performed or has performed for
us
and the result is what i call
transcendent
functionalism that we recognize the
function that
this building is houses in opera house
it's
uh it obviously has a function but why
this
function of having an opera house is in
the form of a chunk of
sea nobody knows and
this not being able to to figure out
what this means is is a kind of
a negative indicator of transcendence if
you can't explain
something at all because it's too
too wild to to too strange to too
unheard of
then this is a a sign of transcendence
and
this type of architecture plays very
strongly with
this sort of with this sort of thing
um and uh finally in terms of
uh i i'd like to address performatism in
a narrative work in this case in
uh in in a movie which i'll get to very
uh
quickly um once more
the basic notions of performatism
it works through double framing the work
will construct
a positive state of experience through
closure by
uh by by creating an enclosed space
this enclosed space is then transcended
in
somewhere in the plot and
here you can you can you can depict it
in this
following way inner frame outer frame is
first subjected to closure and then
there is some form of transcendence
another thing that is very very typical
of
performance narratives is
that the heroes and heroines are
separated they're they're somehow shut
off from other people
this can be psychological it can be
physical or a combination of
both and here once more a uh
a graphic depiction of this sort of
separation
and once more what happens here ideally
in in a performative work
is that these separated characters
transcend their isolation through
bonding with one another so that
the double framing and the bonding work
together
to produce at least or at least suggest
transcendent outcomes so this is the
basic
formula of performance narrative
uh also presented in rather a
schematic simple way now um
the the movie that i'd like to talk
about is
parasite which is the oscar-winning
movie from 2019 it's also i think the
last movie that i saw before
covid struck the last movie i saw in a
movie theater before
covid struck so that
it's still a little bit in my in my
consciousness
the movie is quite complicated i reduced
it
rather drastically to uh to get to the
point
the basic idea if you haven't seen the
movie is that a poor
korean family pretends to be unrelated
to one another
in order to gain access to the house of
a rich family
uh who we see here to the right in the
inner frame
which is the rich families you can think
of as the rich
family's house where most of the action
takes place
uh the at some point the poor family
who are obviously are acting as
parasites in
the sense of the movie's title uh take
over
the family's house and and and live it
up and uh
and have a good time uh unfortunately
what happens there's a further
complication
that there is a second inner frame
within
within the first inner frame and this is
a basement
room where another poor person
the the husband of the former
housekeeper who has been driven out by
this
family is hiding so that
the result is a bloody conflict between
these poor people and as a result
the the father of the poor family kills
the father of the rich family and i
think also the mother kills the
housekeeper's husband resulting in an
enormous
bloodbath i'm sorry if i take away the
the ending of the movie
uh but uh it's unavoidable in this case
uh what happens is that the father hides
in the hidden
basement room where he remains
undiscovered
for i think four years this
the movie makes it sound plausible so we
have to accept this
and he now is now the radically
separated character that i spoke of
earlier in other words he's completely
cut off from all communication with
anyone
he sneaks up in at night and raids the
refrigerator
but otherwise he he can't get out he
can't
he can only communicate with his son
through morse code by uh by
clicking the light switch on in the
house on and off
and by doing so both the son
and the uh and the father
dream of a reunion where the son
will make enough money to buy the house
and and
reunite the the pair and this is shown
as
an imagined scene in the film
uh which you can see here that the the
two
a little bit you can see that the two
figures bond on the threshold between
inside and out and
if you put everything together you'll
see
that the film as a whole the narrative
frame of the film as a whole what i
would call the outer frame
supports this this reunion this this
this
transcendence of of of inside
and out so the two characters uh
bo ideally will bond somewhere
and uh the film suggests that they will
be
reunited or maybe reunited and that the
father will
transcend his self-imposed captivity
so um this is
for this is in my opinion an exemplary
uh an exemplary film in the sense that
it shows how this
double framing can work now
i'd like to make a jump
or perhaps to summarize this
the film forces us to identify with the
desire of the main characters to
transcend what is a seemingly a hopeless
closed-off situation the film does this
using
an a biblical motif which is reunion of
the father with the sun
the film also contains a critique of
capitalism and
social striving but this critique is
somewhat ambivalent it's
uh because we want
the characters to succeed we want them
to become
wealthy we want them to occupy this rich
person's
house and this this the striving
for transcendence in a certain sense
becomes
more important than the ethical problems
raised by
by their actions in doing so so there's
this tension between
uh between doing bad things
or doing somewhat uh illegal things
in order to in order to better yourself
in order to transcend
and then obviously the tension between
that and
and legal things like hurting people
and the film leaves this open the film
remains ambivalent in this sense
and this leads me into a another
field which is a performance culture
in politics and society and
here i think one of the main points
is that proformatism is a reaction to
the complete triumph of global
capitalism i don't think that
there are very very few uh enclaves
where there is no capitalism maybe north
korea maybe
belarus very very few countries there
are very very few countries where
the capitalism is as a economic system
doesn't
function and this replaces
the old post modernist or
notion of a of
of an opposition between a
non-capitalist periphery that is somehow
going to resist
capitalist hegemony and first world
capitalist
domination this uh this this model was
was very important in the 1870s 80s 90s
but i think that in terms of world
economic development it has
it it is now obsolete and
performatism or performances culture is
is a kind of
reaction to this new uh
development what i think post-modernist
culture
does in this situation where capitalism
capitalism is everywhere uh literally
is that it creates
or gives us the ability in culture to
create closed off
singular spaces within this global
capitalism and there are different
possibilities that this offers there's
resistance to capitalism
there is coexistence with capitalism and
there is also
then the the co-optation of of
capitalism which i think
you we find in the in parasite in the
movie that we
just saw that uh uh the movie
uh the movie in a certain sense
encourages us to co-opt uh co-op
capitalism to uh to to better ourselves
or at least it
it suggests that the characters are
doing this
performance culture also plays a role in
what
uh in what i would call post-ideological
politics now post-ideological politics
have been with us for a very long time
we
no longer have two blocks we no longer
have a communist
and a a a capitalist system
and the the grand ideologies as uh
as leotar was want to call them no
longer
exist in this sense but we do have a lot
of politics that is based on
belief whether good bad or
indifferent in other words politics
is now very often oriented towards
performative belief systems and
examples of this would be populism the
relative the populist systems in
uh for governments in poland and hungary
also in america
the government of trump uh culture wars
in particular though the ones raging in
in these countries which are provoked by
the populists
also are indicative of this that belief
becomes
uh almost more important than
traditional ideology
religious fundamentalism in in the
muslim world
but also the the arab spring
which uh which brings forth opposites
in certain sense the opposite values of
religious fundamentalism
uh that individual dignity is now seen
as
as as a goal um obama's yes we can
other miracles your shaftiness in all i
think are also
in indicative of this kind of politics
in which
uh belief which performance
performed relief plays a role and
this is expressed directly in these
slogans
now um um
perhaps the um and then and finally uh
a remark about social media which uh
as we know are omnipresent uh from the
point of view of performatism
uh these social media which obviously
can spread disinformation which can be
create virtual worlds which uh which uh
virtual illusionary worlds uh from the
performance point of view
these social media are able to make
things present
they can make things immediate that
we would otherwise not have access to
and in in this sense you could think of
them as a being
also having performative uh performance
qualities
uh finally uh this is i think the the
last thing which is the
um uh the last uh
uh my last point is
performance and the pandemic which we're
all
obviously uh affected by and
in terms of performatist culture
we've now been unified by the threat of
the virus which
you could think of as an outer frame
that is enclosing everyone
uh we're now all in confined to
enclosed spaces through lockdowns
through quarantines uh
where in in a certain sense these would
be inner frames
we follow rituals that closely resemble
religious practices like
masking avoiding physical contact stress
baking
all things that have religious
implications
of course unconsciously and
uh and and we also try to bond with what
with others in spite of
all these restrictions from uh without
and
finally we're all awaiting an act of
transcendence an act of salvation with a
vaccine the virus mutating to something
less harmful or
or whatever so this is um uh
so so in this rather strange
way grotesque way uh the virus
the the virus acts in a
in in a kind of a performantist way
without of course
being conscious of of doing so
and with that that's the end of my um
that's the end of my
little uh lecture and i will now
return the uh i will now
return the screen to tom mark
um wait a minute
sharing i will stop there
right here we are professor edelman
thank you for for that lecture that was
great
i think there are a couple of questions
that we all have uh what i will do now
um is to uh
bring some people who are participating
on the zoom call
um to this discussion and while i'm
doing so like
would you elaborate a little bit on um
on the relationship between performatism
and the pandemic because you could say
i mean it's obviously it's like the
first no it's not the first time but how
is it different to the
you know spanish flu say 100 years ago
like why is that not related to
performance why is that
virus corona correlated to
to to covet um
well i wouldn't the the the this last uh
the last remarks about
um uh about the covet were
simply to show how how an act
something accidental is is translated
into cultural actions or can be can be
thought of
in terms of a a certain cultural mindset
i don't know enough about the the the
the 1918
pandemic to to really compare it one
thing i do know about it
is is that everybody there there are
very
few um there are very few depictions of
it
um right in cultural in works of culture
which is a little bit different now
there are now um i'm aware there there
there are numerous essays there are also
attempts i think the the new york times
had a competition
for writers um to to express themselves
about
about the pandemic um so
uh the main point is not that the the
the the 1918 pandemic was somehow
modernist in the way it was
it was depicted or in the way it was um
in the way people dealt with it uh
simply because i don't have
i i have no terms of comparison right
okay so but you did do a relationship to
to
uh to corona like and and performance
like where does it come from
like is it just it can't be just
arbitrary that you
say well there are like these
quasi-religious practices we have
and we are enclosed and it can't be just
circumstantial
that's what i mean um it's uh
it's a bit accidental um
but what it does show is that
of course the virus is is an accident in
in in
at least as far as we can tell right um
it's an accident and this accident
simply
for for accidental reasons it fits in
very well
with our present cultural uh mindset
which is the the
the reason that i uh the the reason that
i
that i uh picked it out right but it is
it's essentially accidental right
so so um i mean would you say that
um the the paradigm which you are
describing
as as performatism has permeated our
culture that much
that it's a it's a phenomenon that fits
that kind of
narrative or that kind of yeah exactly
that would that would be the point is
that uh
that it fits in perfectly with
uh with with our cultural mindset and
with our
and with what was going on in in in
culture as a whole or what has been
going on in culture as a whole for the
last
perhaps uh 15 20 years but but it is i
it is accidental though right right i
don't know
if um the participants can
uh uh say something uh or if
they still muted um
can you please use the chat to tell me
if
um if you can say something
because i think i unmuted them but i
don't know
let's see um another
question that i had was about this
framing
okay she was just okay perfect
okay um uh about the framing
so the question that i had was
um how can i employ
and use this model of framing and double
framing to
look at you know works of art because it
all
also seems a little bit arbitrary it's
like like it's it's a cognitive
act that i have to you know uh to use
like how do i use this model to to
assess a work of art you know as a
layman
you know if i if i'm confronted with a
with a movie like parasite
you know what i mean you
basically don't have to you don't have
to
usually don't have to think very hard
because these
type of movies or books or whatever
force you to make identifications that
you would normally not make i think
that's the
that that's the one main criteria if
you're looking for a performance this
work of art
does this work force me to identify
myself with something that normally i
wouldn't identify
myself with like with a knife murderer
in this particular case
right and the the second point is that
is this and this is also very closely
connected to this
problem of identification is there how
is this meant ironically
right is there is is this work making
fun of me
is it making fun of the characters is it
uh
um and uh i don't believe that i think
these
if you take these two criteria as a
layman and apply them to anything that
you read or watch
you'll be able to you'll be able to get
a pretty good idea of what what is
performance
and what is not right also subjectively
without going through all the
theoretical
okay involved okay i think lena has a
question
lena do you hear me yes i do
my camera doesn't work on this computer
right well thank you for
uh for this interesting lecture uh so
you brought out
uh three examples of architecture the
modern functionalistic
skyscraper than the atnt building which
was
postmodern and had these um
sort of ironical uh
applications the um the
chippendale and the
art deco and then the opera house
in hamburg or concert hall in hamburg
which has i think the the bottom part
the red
brick part was was that an original
building that had the
the gray part with the light and the
sort of the waves on top added to it
yes it wasn't originally i think it was
a warehouse of some kind
yeah um and
um so the the first one is strictly
functionalistic and very sort of machine
like then you have the
second one which is the postmodern with
the ironical distance to
something human made in the past and
then you have the opera house that has
a stylized piece of nature namely the
ocean or you could also see the waves on
top as sort of
sails on a sailboat or something very
organic that it that is added to
something non-organic at all
and so i was wondering if there is in
this transcendence
in the um performative
framework is is there a relationship to
nature that is not
there in in the modern and the
post-modern
yeah that's a a a very interesting
question
um in this particular case
i think there is but
in this also in this particular case
it's it's constructed nature
in other words it's not an attempt to
uh integrate nature into directly
into the um into the the into the
architectural structure
uh that would something be something
more more even perhaps more post-modern
that the post-post-modern buildings you
know with grassy roofs and with
that that
the nature around them um
the postmodern or the excuse me the
performance architecture that i've
seen or described up to now tends to to
to be very very constructed and when
nature does appear as sort of when
something natural does appear
then as as a very clearly marked
construct
as as in this case so it's not a back to
nature
type of thing
right right so would you do you see this
do you see this uh epoch in
in culture as uh coming towards an end
or is is this continuing do you see
something else replacing it now
because this is this has really been
going on for 30 years which according to
your
definition of post-modernism was also 30
years
yeah basically it should be it should be
on its way out
but i haven't seen uh
seen anything that is is is radically
different from it up to now
it's also possible that i have uh
performative blinders on that i'm simply
uh so so taken by uh by by the theory
itself that i don't see these things
this is also
possible in cognitive terms but
up to now i haven't seen anything that
would
uh that that would suggest that there's
something
radically different out there that is is
replacing it at the moment
but i'm always open suggestions you just
mentioned
nature so i was wondering i mean some of
the new architecture
is as you said i mean there there's
grass on the roof and your
uh i
i would even guess that even though it
doesn't look like nature but as you said
it it's a
it's a human uh replica replication of
nature
it might actually be a co2 neutral
building i don't know
the hamburg um concept building here
uh i don't know i'm just i'm just
you know thinking that it it may not
look as if it's in harmony with nature
but it might actually be
but then there is a visual aesthetic
harmony with nature which you brought it
up yourself
which is so is nature integrated into
the
architecture and that might actually be
one of the future
uh or what is currently in the making
because i mean it takes a while
to to create a building so i mean if you
compare to
fashion for instance that that shifts
two to three times per year you have a
new collection three of two or three
four times per year and so you design it
within six months before it's in the
market but but a
building a concert hall i mean that's 10
15 years in the making maybe
so what we see as architecture now was
an idea for a very long i mean
just an idea a long time ago
so so the the trends the uh
the values the aesthetics that manifest
themselves in architecture
uh half
they were they emerged earlier than we
see them now because it takes a time it
takes a while to build it
yeah that's entirely possible i i i
kind of keep my eyes peeled for new
buildings when i'm in
in different cities uh up to now i
haven't seen
anything like that but as i said and i
think as you also properly said that
these in architecture it takes a a
longer time
very often for these things to to be
realized and
but as of now i haven't seen anything
drastically different from from these
performatist
buildings
well can i chime in just for a second
because like uh
staying on topic of of this
philharmony it's like um the that the
architect used nature as far underst as
i understand it was
a means to an end because it seems as
you said like a
like a transcendent heavenly thing
appearing as like nature as water but
what's what's prime is or what's
important is the
experience of heavenly beauty uh
and and and and what's the point it's
not the point
that it's uh imitating nature but it's
more the the experience of
beauty and and and some
outer worldly form manifesting on top of
of the factory hall and so i think
that's that's
uh what it's about it's not about nature
it's it's about the experience
um mediated through imitation of nature
do i get that right that's absolutely
precisely what i would have said is that
nature is a part of it
um but what is what is really most
important is this this notion of
of transcendence of somehow
apprehending transcendence um
and there are other aspects of the
building that that also
that demonstrate that i think that if
it's it's it's broken off in different
places that the top is
is separated from the bottom it seems to
float on the bottom
it has other aspects that all convey
that sort of
of impossibility that that suggests
transcendence
so you have to discard disbelief
actively
and so and i think that that is also is
could you describe that also as a frame
that you have to set that frame to
discard
you know you mentioned in your book like
the american what what's the movie
american
american beauty american beauty or or
life of pi
where you have like these opposing
descriptions
of what happened on the boat uh and
you have like like one realistic and one
uh
more mythical or more fantastic way of
describing the events but the the
the the work of art forces you
to to maybe choose the more unrealistic
more
fantastical one because it it
points to a higher form of love or
experience
you know and so it does does
does that is that a framing
to discard disbelief and to to to choose
also
or or what what is that do you
know about him yes i know i know what
you're saying it's
it's uh in ideal terms it's not
it's not a cognitive decision in other
words it's not a
it's not the result of some sort of
reflection about do i want to discard
belief
and uh rather a disbelief and do i want
to believe
it's it's it's rather a case of of of uh
belief imposing itself right and so that
i guess
i can't resist this belief there's a see
i do not know your book i only heard
this lecture now so
uh but the story of pi uh
there's a a crucial line in in
in that movie um which is that the
reason why he was telling the story in
that way was because reality was too
unbearable yeah so the real story i mean
what actually happened on that boat um
i think his mother was killed uh by one
of the
sailors or something like that so um
so he turns this into a parable and it's
an entirely symbolic
myth myth that he creates yeah because
he simply cannot bear to tell the truth
yeah or the the objective truth but it
becomes
a spiritual truth exactly yeah
um and if we look at that um
concert hall there's some
some of the same there because i mean it
it's the
the original red brick building is that
that's the that's the
if that was an old warehouse of of
modernism
and of capitalism and of of all this
maybe unbearable stuff then it has this
piece of beauty on top of it
which becomes a narrative and it it's
also i mean that is reflecting the sea
it is on the harbor
yes i even lived
so i wonder if if uh if part of that
performance
is really because there is something
that is so un unbearable
that we have to beautify it we have to
turn it into a narrative that is grander
than that unbearable reality that we're
actually facing
um in a certain sense yes
one thing that i didn't talk about uh
much in the lecture because it would
have been
too complicated and leads into all kinds
of philosophical questions is that
um that this this this type of mindset
aesthetics yes i can't even pronounce it
as statisticizes
reality which is exactly what you uh
what you described here is that
um the tendency is to
uh to present ugly reality or to to
regard reality as something ugly as
something that is
threatening and that to try to make it
bearable
through the aesthetic means
and this leads also to spiritualization
at least to aesthetization
and these things very often go uh go go
hand in hand
and these the like the life of pi
views this is something positive i think
that's that's you would agree with that
the book is not making fun of
a pie or who follow his
uh who who choose the more beautiful
version
um it's an attitude it's a mindset that
you can
then yourself reproject onto the world
and maybe cause that ugly uh ugly world
to to
to to to become better in some way i
think that's how an ethics of
of of performatism would work
i i think the same thing is in the
painting with the
yellow raincoat i mean that's uh this is
a
very bleak uh surrounding
and it's gray and it's raining and it's
uh basically europe and freaking october
like now um and so
that is that is kind of unbearable and
you know that you have like four months
ahead with the same kind of
crappy weather so uh and in that you
have that
bright yellow raincoat and a child maybe
even playing in the
in the water and the rain there so i
think there is that kind of
you know ping-pong between the
unbearable and
and the beauty and the um
making it bearable yes that's that's
that's very definitely a
a part of of performatism and it's a
as i said it's it's a it's a it's a kind
of a gut reaction against
uh postmodernism which tends to
uh simply stick its finger in the wound
continually in other words to uh to to
to
to to to demonstrate to us that any
attempt to
to be to experience beauty or experience
anything higher
it is an illusion that will keep us from
facing
uh facing harsh reality so
you i mean both both mindsets are
possible
but in cultural terms i think this uh
the the post-modern mindset set has
outlived itself
that it's uh it's now perceived as
simply being
irony for the sake of of irony's sake
it's uh
um people want this this this kind of
uh these these kind of higher higher
experiences
so how do you how do you see
beauty because i mean that is the
the concert hall i mean it is beautiful
um it also has a certain kind of
ugliness i was actually there and when
you go up with the escalator it it's
you have to go through that sort of tube
of ugliness before you get to the beauty
of the building
um but
so but i guess i mean beauty is in the
eye of the beholder
but still there is something objectively
beauty beautiful
in that concert hall building and
there's something beautiful in that
childhood the red
in the yellow uh raincoat
so so the fact that we dare
we dare appreciate beauty show beauty
have beauty
and i mean that is also transcendent
emotion
because it it connects us with something
deeper inside ourselves
if we dare uh subjugate ourselves to
beauty and just experience it as beauty
my sentiments exactly this is yeah so
this is
also one of the i think one of the main
principles
driving principles behind this kind of
cultural development
but so i would like to
because you bring in the modern and the
post-modern and both of those
are very individualistic i mean the the
the individual plays a really strong
role in both
epochs in our history and philosophy and
society
but before that we had a traditional
culture and that's where we have
religion
and that's where we uh used beauty
to connect people
and to build societies and cohesion
and to transcend collectively perhaps
even but also as an individual
to aim for something higher than the
human
uh society i mean the posterity the
divine whatever we want to call it um
so do you see in i mean
something beyond uh the performative
that could relate back to something that
is also connecting people because
uh the i mean the child in that painting
is very
very much alone yeah
um yes that's um
it's this is a big problem in other
words
ideally i suppose that this performance
kind of
ethics that i was talking about that you
let beauty or
some sort of higher form of experience
work upon yourself and then you project
it back onto others
would result in collective uh
some sort of a collective mindset that
is uh
some sort of collective experience that
positive in a certain way when you of
course look at our
reality and that the pandemic was is
actually a good example of that the
pandemic were all
exposed to the same external
factors in the pandemic for the most
part
and uh of course it doesn't quite work
that way
that uh you have people who deny the
deny the existence of the virus you have
uh
it it's it's not quite as uh um
is the result is not quite as uplifting
as what
one might one might hope but but what
you say is also true that this would be
the ideal of
if performatism would be would realize
itself in a in a positive way this is
the direction that it would
go in uh unfortunately it's it's
probably
not going to happen the the way things
the way things look
how do you mean
i mean you you you think that we will
remain as
fragmented as societies individuals and
societies
as as we have been for the past 30 and
60 years
or so you don't think that will change
um i'm not a prophet i
i am also not a sociologist this is
something that uh
this is this is more uh something that
sociologists
or students of um of of religion would
have to
would have to look at more closely uh it
will be certainly be
interesting to see whether the pandemic
leads to any sort of
new cohesiveness um perhaps in certain
regards it
it has and will but at the moment of
course we're in the middle of it and
it's
it's very difficult to tell
i mean the interesting thing is that the
pandemic is actually the first time
uh in human history that we all work
together
and you know it's like we have these
daily exercises
and this lockdowns and washing hands and
whatever but this is
basically like a like daily exercise
we're all doing together
yeah and so that's basically the first
time in history that that happened
yeah that we all work together and so
that's and we're we're all on
soon together separate but we're all
zoomed together this is once more the
paradox of
the the paradox that i was talking about
also with social media we're all
together
we're all here and at the same time
we're uh
we're obviously uh simply little pixels
on on
on the screen uh so there's a
there's a kind of uh um there's a kind
of split in in this
in the way we we deal with this
there there is also a shared sense of
irony towards
2020 i mean that has become a thing
i mean this this year is so weird and
it's all around the globe it's like
seven eight billion people suffering
from the same
silly year where everything just seems
to go haywire
and everybody everybody notices it
yeah exactly and once more whether this
actually uh in the final analysis
results in some sort of you know basal
change in human consciousnesses
is of course is asking a lot that's
it's it's possible but it's at the
moment it's
it's not clear that that will happen
that's why why are you saying
consciousness because
lena if i may because lena is uh she
studied uh theology if i if i remember
right and she wrote a couple of books
uh on metamodernism for example and and
stuff like that
uh the nordic secret and um what i was
wondering like if
is there you know because metamodernism
connects
cultural stages also like very broadly
speaking to
cognitive development and
self-authorship and self-transcendence
in a kind of way so if you look at
performatism
is there uh is is there
an increase of some form of world
building of sense making of
of complexity of of yeah say
psychological development a need to to
participate or to create
uh such works of art or is it like
completely
separated just like cultural phenomenon
as a cultural phenomenon um
that that's very hard to say um one of
the my
my basic ideas is that uh that
performatism
uh works mainly on the the level of
intuition
in other words that uh it's um
it does raise your consciousness or
change your consciousness in a certain
way
uh but not through reflection uh it's
it's
mainly through uh the the these
the experiencing of these uh higher
states of
of of of whatever love beauty
these positive higher states that are
being imposed on us
um so it's mainly mainly intuitive
so that i don't i've never
thought about how it could be translated
or transferred into
into into into into actual
self-improvement
in in that in that sense i don't uh uh
well not so much self-improvement it's
maturational it's natural it's
maturation yeah
um yeah that's it it's it's certainly
possible but
like i said this is it's it's a little
bit out of my
uh uh out of my uh out of my box it's
uh i i simply haven't
haven't dealt with that right
but you might i mean like like one one
of lena's books
deals with you know works of art
you know in in the german history
like and how they uh you know
connect very well to stages of
psychological development development
and that
what what what fish there and hegel and
and shelling and and good
and what they're all like we're up
against or
creating anyone has to have to correct
me if i'm
saying this wrong but you know so like
these were the ideals put
forward by the german philosophers and
can very well describe by psychology
today and so you have to think about
you know when if if they created works
of art and literature and
so like what kind of psychological stage
of development
corresponds to performatism or
metamodernism or
whatever you know it's like it has to
come from somewhere
you know it's not like arbitrary and
creating
itself out of itself you know what i
mean it's like there has to be
a form of cognitive mindset
to you know to approach yeah i would
i would be able to um yes
to deal with the term cognitive mindset
i think that's that's that's that's
that's more like what it is
uh i can't say i can't say anything
about how that ties in with
uh german philosophy i would have to
read leona's book which i would be
interested in looking at but at the
moment i can't really
comment on it i like to hear that i
can't comment on it
directly
right so i think it was the um
or let me put it in a different way i
mean
the what we call art uh
the difference between art and
entertainment and we're we're in
we're in the the field of the aesthetics
now
so that can be architecture that can be
art that can be fashion
but it's any kind of symbolic
representation of
what is important to us and
the way that i distinguish between
entertainment and art is that
entertainment confirms
uh and reproduces what we already know
so it makes us feel safe but
art expands our symbolic world
and it expands what we're capable of
communicating to one another
and so we have different areas of the
arts we've got
architecture we've got music we've got
design we got
um poetry got theater i mean there are
paintings all these different kinds of
arts and they're all
expanding our our symbolic world and our
way of being in this world and so
because
the arts expand our
symbolic world and we do not have yet
the
symbols that it is creating it will have
to be
the intuition of those who are sort of
on the fringes of
of the culture those who come up with a
sentiment that hasn't been put into
symbols yet who create those symbols and
then
we call them artists um
or great architects because they
captured something
far enough in advance that was still
somehow meaningful to the investors in
the
buildings that allowed them to design
the kind of building and build it and
here we are with with
architecture that someone i mean that
that points forward
but was actually conceived maybe 5 10 or
15 years earlier
and that expresses who we are or who we
are
about to become um and
that makes it all right so yes we are in
the intuitive
field uh but that intuition
it it points in a direction
yes i completely agree that uh in other
words
um there is this at some point in the
mid 90s it's it's very hard to say
where or when it exactly started this
this this this intuition of creative
people began and uh
it it it it began in
it began all over the place it began as
i said i started out in russia and i
quickly discovered
it was it was in america it was
eventually in germany also
uh so that uh and this intuition also
also spread to become a collective
um almost a collective consciousness
and it's even trickled down i think it's
trickled down to
to popular culture to what you called
entertainment that right
yeah and so i mean if if we were to
um and one of the things that's
interesting right now because of social
media and because of technology
um in the west we have we have driven
this
uh development since the last 500 years
and there has been a sort of a natural
barrier between our culture and other
cultures because
there wasn't the communicational tools
to spread all this information all these
stories and
symbols but with mass media and
particularly with social media
500 years of aesthetics
are suddenly worldwide in no time
and this whole um conflict or
clash between the the traditional
society and
aesthetics and values and the modern
society
and aesthetics and values and
post-modern with the irony
uh and also with the performatism here
that is like all over the place around
the globe
simultaneously so there are a lot of
cultures
outside the western civilization
that have to face both the traditional
society and
modernism and post-modernism and this
performance-ism
and you know everything simultaneously
and they have a tremendous challenge
figuring out which is what and
and how to navigate this we after all
are have had sort of a progressive
development
of these increasingly complex
and self-referential aesthetic systems
yeah i i once again i i agree that
this is uh this is the new uh challenge
it's it's no longer this peripheral
these peripheral peripheral traditional
societies that are
uh adamantly opposed to to western
culture or being swallowed up by western
culture
you see fusions you see new fusions in
all these cultures i mean
i've had i was in china several years
ago and you could see this very very
intensively how they
take their own culture and they uh
they they merge it with uh with with
with western culture in
in in new synthetic ways um
i that that's the the culture that i've
had most the most experience with but i
think it's also taking place in the arab
world
that uh i have quite a few people in the
air in the arab world who are interested
in performatism
i think for that reason is that they're
searching for some sort of
of way to to fuse their own culture with
let us say western concepts of of
individualism
uh the arab spring for example
was about that to a great extent so
these are very very dynamic
processes that are going on all over the
place
and they're not just negative it's not
just the
west swallowing up swallowing up
traditional cultures these traditional
cultures
adapting and uh and also
renewing themselves that that would also
be the ideal of
the performance for performative ideal
in this case as these
these cultures were able to renew
themselves within this
global capitalism which is really
universal
yep
so do you see uh i mean since you're
professor of the slavic uh literature or
languages
uh literature literature so how do you
how do you see it in uh
in those areas uh in in those areas it's
um it depends on where you are in in
russia it's it's rather depressing
or wasn't that always the story it's
almost
it's almost always been that way but
it's
simply particularly depressing obviously
russia has a very
long history of of
of mixing spirituality and literature
uh you need to only mention telstoy
dostoyevsky
uh but it's it's still a very strong
feature of
of russian culture but it has now
um given way to a kind of of
of hopelessness this is the one uh the
one path that's being taken it's uh
it's really hopelessness in the face of
of the present uh present regime and the
other
is a kind of um is a kind of
uh uh enjoyment and
and and exalting in in
in imperialism in in russia so that you
have a
a right-wing literature which is
um which aestheticizes imperial russian
imperialism
uh often in a in a very clever way and
and then you have the
the more progressive or liberal elements
that have
that that are starting to give up that
are starting to to to resign completely
and
this the situation is is not as i said
not
is is is is depressing
so how how about uh places like
ukraine or belarus or georgia
or any of these other um
non-russian uh
countries and where there are in many
places
even large russian minorities
but a strong urge to create a new sense
of collective self
um as as independent states
yeah this is a very difficult problem
that is
the the each individual country
solves in a different way so that it's i
can't go into
a great deal of detail here as my my
main interests are
or also my linguistic capabilities are
confined
to uh to the czech republic and to a
certain extent to
to poland so that i can't really uh talk
about
uh the developments in in ukraine
or or georgia or or any of these places
with with any uh
authority um there's a definite tendency
though
to um
it's it's it's it's a difficult process
in all these countries because
they are split between populism
in both in political and in aesthetic
terms you could say and
between a more open approach to to
things and also a
more openness a greater opening sports
western culture
because i mean they really saw the
downside of of modernism
uh or modernity with with stalin
and the soviet union
yes you could say that but the the the
result was there there have been really
there have been sociological demographic
studies done of this and
basically they retain the this
autocratic uh mindset
this is one of the right sociological
problems of
in particular in in russia that putin is
is actively supported i think by a
majority of the population for these
reasons
so do you see that as something that is
older than the
than the modern
the modernity that they encountered as
the authoritarian communist state
uh or is it something that was created
by that
that's that's that's a that's very hard
to answer because there's been
it's it's such it's been so continuous
that uh
there's never really been a civil
society in russia or only varied for
very very short periods if at all
and for that reason there's a the this
sort of
autocratic uh anti-democratic mindset
has
was always there and is is very
difficult to get rid of
yep
so any more questions or
pressing issues they know
no i'm good you're good interesting very
uh very nice conversation thank you yes
very nice conversation here too i was
uh so i'll try to take a look at at one
of your books and see what's going on
there
and uh yeah yeah one one thing that
always
interests me and i never had the chance
is like what what happens
when uh they are like uh proponents of
different
uh uh systems of thought you know
dealing with post-post-modernism
say metamodernism performatism integral
and
a couple of uh uh developmental
psychologist bringing them all to a
table
and trying to hash out you know okay
what are we talking about actually
because it seems to me that uh all these
views are
kind of grand and and holistic and but
at the same time have like a very
particular approach to a certain kind of
phenomena
phenomenon and so like what okay what
what are we actually talking about
you know is it a cultural phase is a is
it just
like a theory about art is it is a
developmental stage is it a cultural
stage it's a movement
you know all these lingering open
questions if we deal with okay what is
what comes after post-modernism you know
and so there's like
if you have different proponents of of
different
uh uh schools that would be interesting
to see okay is there
maybe a meta narrative that can be de
constructed
or uh experienced uh if
if we bring all these different
perspectives to one table you know
you know what i'm saying it's like that
that would be like very interesting to
me too
yeah this is one general problem is that
there is
there's there's no discourse about
post-post-modernism in other words there
are many different
approaches and there is but
there is no sort of overarching
discussion of of what is going on so
that
um i tend to usually have contact with
the literary scholars
and uh don't get into much contact with
the the integral people or with
with the psychology um
so so it would indeed be interesting to
get that kind of discourse uh going but
at the present moment in academia it's
very difficult right
i mean and at the same time
postmodernism faces the same problem
because uh depends on on who you are
asking
post-modernism is this and then
post-modernism is that and you know then
it's like
you know there's no i mean like we can
agree on on certain characteristics like
irony or skepticism against all my
but this doesn't say nothing basically
it's just you know it's just like
still still at this point
nobody knows exactly what post-modernism
is because there's no overarching
consensus about it you know it's like
but
uh that's uh unfortunately that's fairly
normal right
the same thing if you you can apply to
romanticism you can apply that
you have the same the the exact same
uh excuse me you have the exact same um
uh problems with the romanticism uh to a
certain extent with realism
that depending on who you are and
depending on what
sources you use you'll come to very
different conclusions actually
i think that's something that at least
as a scholar that i it's something that
i'm used to
right really surprised me that there is
no
uh consensus but uh i think that
what what you can actually do is is what
what you suggested you can agree on
certain very basic
things such as irony such as this
critique of grand narrative right a few
things that
that everybody really does agree on and
that
use that as as as a starting point right
at least as a
as as common ground for for a discussion
right so but you think there there could
be uh
like a common ground be found between
different proponents of
postmodern schools or is there something
to
discover or is uh or like a
common denominator or isn't
um yes i i i would think sorry
it's hard to say if there's there's you
know one common denominator but
uh i've tried to to
find a common denominator or common
denominators
with within literary scholarship and you
can actually do it
it's possible um i i haven't ventured
any farther than that simply because
it's it's
it's a bit too too far outside my field
but
my tendency would be to think that it is
uh
possible at least at least partially
possible right
so i'm optimistic in that so that we by
i mean like
the problem probably is that we're still
in that phase
and and the historians and the the
philosophers
you know really are able to paint a
bigger picture if we all already have
left that kind of
cultural phase or or whatever it is so
we're still in the midst of it
and so it's like very hard to hash out
where
you know the threats between
metamodernism
performatism demodernism transmodernism
integral where
where all these interconnecting threats
are really are so that we can maybe say
you know like
and post modernity when it's about irony
and critique and
skepticism that you know that pos post
mode on stage is
yeah about what about what is it you
know what what is that
you know and for lack of a better word
what is the essence of
yeah yeah yeah now this is uh
this this is in fact a problem and when
you're in
something in something that it's it's
hard to
it's hard to tell what's going on
um uh that's this is
quite true of anything it's an ongoing
process
like i said i'm always looking i'm
always i think lena said you know is
this going to
is something new coming is something is
this going to end and i'm always
kind of looking for that um at some
point it will happen
but it's it's once you have this mindset
whatever it is whether it's
post-modernist modernist or
post-post-modernism it's it's very hard
to get out of this mindset
right so yes okay i i think
um no but you know
like you know maybe maybe the last
question if nobody else
uh asked but you know it's like when i
look at especially like the the
early forms of metamodernism or integral
it's like it's it's like a lot
about oscillating between previous
eras or epochs or paradigms or stages of
development
and so it's like you you find a middle
ground between oscillating between the
modernist project
and the the postmodern project and that
is then defined
as you know the the integral or the
metamode on the stage
so but i always have the feeling okay
that that may be true but there's also
something more
right some some like like with an
emergence emergence
doesn't really only happen with
integrating what comes before
but also creating something new that
it's not necessarily
understandable by the elements which
created it in the first place
so emergence is always always there's
always a new information it's not
just oscillating between what came
before
and so i think like okay what you know
maybe it's it's a new understanding of
of
beauty and uh transcendence
you know so maybe maybe like this i mean
the the one of the final stages of of of
of the keegan robert keegan model of
development actually
is it self-transcendent is that the
actual transforming
it's self-transforming yes so
um but there's also like some
but you could also i mean i when when uh
i wrote the the nordic secret i mean i
i kept writing it wrong and because it
it made more sense to call it
transcending
right uh so i had to go back and uh
actually check what we have been writing
um so yeah so cell transforming self
transcending
right um and i think what what we're
experiencing now
is that i mean there is this
hunger for a meaning and depth
uh which we could not have in the
post-modern
era i mean you were not allowed to
actually feel
something really genuine
and you always have to distance yourself
from it and you can't live like that
i mean you can you can have it as a
coping mechanism
but but it's not it's not a life and i i
think that is where we're
where we're heading and it's also why we
see populism
um and people are reacting to this sort
of
self distancing
yeah this is yeah this system i once
more agree
that this is a this is the
direction we're heading in that it's
it's very difficult uh
even in during the time of
post-modernism i'm not really sure that
very many people actually
lived this kind of disillusioned
life that was being propagated in in
high culture and in
philosophy in philosophy and in in
obviously also in
the halls of major universities i i'm
not sure that
that was a really uh really a viable
a viable lifestyle even then
but it does i mean it does do something
to culture
when you cannot be sincere and and
and when i mean of course you're sincere
in your relationships and your personal
relationships and you
uh you can exp you can experience it
in your life and you can have you know
intimate relationships you can have all
these things
and as you say you're absolutely right
it did not
you know define everyday life and the
way that we actually
lived our lives but if the acceptable
discourse
if the culture the pop culture
all the and even the arts tell us that
nothing matters it is really hard to
have
at least in the public sphere a
meaningful
discussion or debate um and to
stand up for something that really means
something to you
or to others yeah this is yeah
so so so at the collective level uh so
maybe at the
individual level we have had the
sincerity but at the collective level
it has been it's been very hard to
uh to you know take things seriously
and and here we are and you know
you got people who know nothing about
science just
deconstructing or thin i mean
rejecting uh science um
and just taking it apart from
an ill-informed place
yeah this is uh yeah once more
i completely agree we must
[Laughter]
all right good i think
i think we have it for today yes that's
yes
president thank you very much that you
took the time
and uh for this lecture and and
for this for this talk
uh my pleasure yes